Finding Aid for Joyce Jones Papers, 1930-1980
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Joyce Jones Papers 1930-1980
Jones, Joyce, 1897-1980.
2 linear feet
85235 Aa 2
University of Michigan botanist and Ann Arbor handweaver. Papers and photographs relating to her participation in various local art organizations, especially the Ann Arbor Art Association, the Ann Arbor Street Art Fair, the fine arts section of the Michigan Academy of Science, Arts, and Letters; and her participation in handweaving associations, including the Ann Arbor Handweaver's Guild, the Handweaver's Guild of America, the Michigan League of Handweavers, and the handweaving classes at the Y.M.-Y.W.C.A.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Joyce Jones' son, Alan H. Jones (donor no. 4583 ) and came to the library in 1983.
The collection is open to research.
Joyce Hedrick Jones was born July 1, 1897 in Fort Recovery, Ohio. She received a bachelor's and master's degree from Miami of Ohio University and came to Ann Arbor in 1929. In 1933, Joyce married Volney H. Jones, a well-known professor of ethnobotany at the University of Michigan. During the next 30 years, Joyce Jones worked at the University of Michigan Herbarium, first as research assistant, then assistant curator, and finally curator of lichens. She also published articles on lichens based on her research during the 1930's and 1940's.
In addition to her career, Joyce Jones was interested in artistic endeavors involving weaving. She was a prominent weaver in Ann Arbor, originating the weaving program at the Y.M.-Y.W.C.A., and was one of the founding members of both the Ann Arbor Handweavers' Guild and the Michigan League of Handweavers. Also, Jones was an active member of the Ann Arbor Art Association, and worked as registrar and demonstrator of weaving at the annual Ann Arbor Street Art Fair until her death.
Involved in numerous organizations, Mrs. Jones often held positions of leadership. For example, she served on the Board of Directors for the Y.M.-Y.W.C.A. and also acted as chairperson of the Adult Program Committee and the Program and Personnel Expediting Committee. She also served as either treasurer, secretary, or vice-president in organizations such as the Women's Alliance of the First Unitarian Church and others. Mrs. Jones was a member of professional organizations as well, such as the Michigan Academy of Science, Arts and Letters, and the Mycological Society of America. She died February 2, 1980.
The Joyce Jones Papers cover the period of her life in Ann Arbor, 1930-1980. While there is some material relating to her research on lichens, mostly articles from the 1930's and 1940's, the bulk of the collection concerns her passion for handweaving.
The collection has been divided into four series: Personal, Art Associations, Handweaving Associations, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor Art Fairs (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Ann Arbor Young Men's-Young Women's Christian Association (Mich.); Ann Arbor Art Association.; Ann Arbor Handweaver's Guild.; Artists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Art--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Arts--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies, etc.; Hand weaving.; Handweavers Guild of America.; Jones, Joyce, 1897-1980.; Michigan Academy of Science, Arts, and Letters.; Michigan League of Handweavers.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Women artists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor Art Fairs (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.)--1961-1969.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Streets.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; Art.; Art festivals.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Main Street (Ann Arbor, Mich.); South University Avenue (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Streets--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Weaving.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Personal
  The Personal series deals with Jones' background and career at the University of Michigan Herbarium, from the 1920's until the late 1950's. Included are a variety of articles on lichen that she published, as well as miscellaneous correspondence relating to handweaving.
  - Biographical Information (Box 1)
  - Articles on Lichen by Joyce Hedrick 1930-1948 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Notes re: Lichen (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence undated, 1975 (Box 1)
- Art Associations
  The Art Associations series is composed of the records of the Ann Arbor Art Association, the Ann Arbor Street Art Fair, and the Michigan Academy of Science, Arts and Letters, along with single folders dealing with the Ann Arbor Winter Art Fair and the Free Arts Festival. Within the separate series, the researcher will find minutes, reports, and programs, along with sparse amounts of correspondence. Jones, at various times in her life, was on the Board of Directors of the Art Association, and served as registrar of the annual Ann Arbor Street Art Fair for over fifteen years. The records reflect these positions. Overall, however, there are many gaps, both chronologically and in volume that indicate these records are not complete. The Michigan Academy of Science, Arts and Letters series, for example, consists solely of organizational material that does not relate to Mrs. Jones personally.
  - Ann Arbor Art Association 1959-1975
    - Joyce Jones Material 1961-1971 (Box 1)
    - Board Meeting Minutes 1964-1967 (Box 1)
    - Membership Lists 1959-1975 (Box 1)
    - Sales Chairman Reports 1966-1969 (Box 1)
    - Shows/Exhibitions undated, 1966-1974, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Organizational materials 1962-1975 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Street Art Fair 1960-1979
    - Minutes 1967-1975 (Box 1)
    - Annual Reports 1965-1975, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Artist's Location and Media 1967-1972, 1977-1979 (Box 1)
    - Registrations 1965-1966 (Box 1)
    - Participating Artists 1966-1972, 1974-1979 (Box 1)
    - Initial Location Layout Blueprint 1961 (Box 1)
    - Programs and Information 1960-1979, 15 folders (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Winter Art Fair 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - Free Arts Festival 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Academy of Science, Arts and Letters (Fine Arts Section) 1941-1970
    - Board Meeting Minutes 1944-1964 (Box 1)
    - By-Laws 1942-1962 (Box 1)
    - Treasurer's Reports 1946-1949, 1952, 1957, 1961 1965,1970 (Box 1)
    - Historian's Record Book 1941-1960 (Box 1)
    - Historian's Material 1951-1955, 1959 (Box 2)
    - Membership Lists 1951-1969 (Box 2)
    - Newsletters 1960-1967 (Box 2)
    - Exhibitions' Material 1944-1969 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, undated 1942-1963 (Box 2)
    - Organization Materials 1948-1960 (Box 2)
- Handweaving Associations
  The Handweaving Associations series consists of records of the Ann Arbor Handweaver's Guild and the Handweavers Guild of America, among others. Jones was one of the founding members of both organizations. She also served as Dye Editor for the Handweaver's Guild's publication Dye Pot. Further records in this series concern the Michigan League of Handweavers, the Michigan Craftsmen's Council, the Shuttlecraft Guild, and the Y.M.-Y.W.C.A. Once again, the files are rarely personal in nature, being primarily Jones' collection of printed information from these societies.
  - Ann Arbor Handweaver's Guild 1958-1980
    - Joyce Jones Correspondence March 1959-January 1974 (Box 2)
    - Minutes of Meetings 1962-1964 (Box 2)
    - Constitution/By-Laws 1957, 1972, 1976 (Box 2)
    - Membership Lists 1960-1980 (Box 2)
    - Newsletters 1974-1977 (Box 2)
    - Yearly Programs 1962-1976 (Box 2)
    - Activities of Guild 1958-1977 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Handweaver's Guild of America 1969-1972
    - Joyce Jones Correspondence undated, August 1969-June 1972 (Box 2)
    - Materials on dyeing for Dye Pot (Box 2)
    - Organization Materials September 1969-June 1972 (Box 2)
  - Michigan League of Handweavers 1957-1979
    - Joyce Jones Correspondence undated, August 1957-September 1977 (Box 2)
    - Handbooks 1961-1974 (Box 2)
    - Annual Reports 1961-1970 (Box 2)
    - Board Meeting Minutes 1959-1972 (Box 2)
    - Membership Lists undated, 1963, 1968 (Box 2)
    - League Letter (newsletter) 1963-1970 (Box 2)
    - League Letter (newsletter) 1973-1975 (Box 2)
    - League Letter (newsletter) 1975-1979 (Box 2)
    - Annual Conferences 1959-1961 (Box 2)
    - Annual Conferences 1964 (Box 2)
    - Annual Conferences 1965 (Box 2)
    - Annual Conferences 1966 (Box 2)
    - Annual Conferences 1967 (Box 2)
    - Annual Conferences 1968 (Box 2)
    - Annual Conferences 1969 (Box 2)
    - Annual Conferences 1970 (Box 2)
    - Annual Conferences 1971-1973, 1975 (Box 2)
    - Organizational Materials (Box 2)
    - Michigan Craftsmen's Council
      - General Materials, early 1960s (Box 2)
      - Conference October 1967 (Box 2)
  - Shuttlecraft Guild/Joyce Jones
    - Correspondence 1965-1967 (Box 2)
  - Y.M.-Y.W.C.A. 1955-1970
    - Adult Program Committee Minutes and Information 1959-1968 (Box 2)
    - Program and Personnel Expediting Committee Minutes and Reports 1955-1956 (Box 2)
    - Committee Reports 1959-1960 (Box 2)
    - Weaving and Macramé 1960-1970 (Box 2)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series includes a photograph album of Ann Arbor Street Art Fairs, 1960-1965. There is also a folder of Jones with others and with her works of art and with the artwork of others.
  - Photograph album of Ann Arbor Street Art Fairs 1960-1965 (Box 2)
  - Photographs of Jones with others and with her works of art and with the artwork of others (Box 2)